Guide to the James McNamara Papers WAG.129
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
James McNamara Papers
Bulk, 1980-1999
1945-1999
WAG.129
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
11.0 linear feet (11 boxes)
James McNamara was an organizer and served in a number of staff positions for the International Ladies Garment Workers Union in the 1950s and 1960s. He then went on to hold a variety of positions at the New York City and state levels in which he engaged in negotiations, enforcement and investigative activities in relation to the building trades and the construction industry. He worked on investigations for the New York State Organized Crime Task Force and the New York County District Attorney’s Office (Labor Racketeering Unit) before his retirement in 1992. The collection contains background material and legal files relating to investigations of the Carpenters, Mason Tenders, Painters, Plumbers, Service Employees (Local 32 B-J) and New York area Teamsters unions. Also included are files on jurisidictional matters relating to the Building Trades Employers Association and files on the investigation of Brian McLaughlin as president of the New York City Central Labor Council.
McNamara, James
Provenance
The papers were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, NYU by James McNamara in a number of installments, beginning in 1996.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Blum Papers. (Wagner #100)
Interview with James McNamara in Burton Hall Union Democracy Project Oral History Collection. (OH #34)
Carpenters for a Stronger Union Records. (Wagner #66)
Daniel French Papers. (Wagner #101)
Burton Hall Papers. (Wagner #87)
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 282, Fear of Reprisal Ends (FORE) Records. (Wagner #107)
Frank Schonfeld Papers. (Wagner #27)
United Tradeswomen Records. (Wagner #102)
Separated Materials
Photographs have been separated to the Non-Print Department of the Tamiment Library.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically by subject within each series.
The collection is divided into 8 Series:
I. United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1970-1999
II. Mason Tenders Local of the Laborers International Union of North America (LIUNA), 1985-1996
III. International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9, 1967-1995
IV. United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipefitting Industry, Plumbers Local #2 (Manhattan), 1964-1997
V. Service Employees International Union, Local 32 B-J, 1954-1999
VI. International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1968-1998
VII. Building Trades Employers Association, 1945-1997
VIII. Unprocessed Material, 1990s-2000s
Historical/Biographical Note
A native of New York City, James McNamara grew up in a working-class family. His father worked for the MTA as a motorman and was a member of the Transport Workers Union. Young McNamara attended Cooperstown Academy, in Cooperstown, New York, but was expelled from the Academy after organizing a student protest. McNamara worked at Yankee Stadium where he operated the turnstile to admit people into the stadium. He organized the vendors at the ball park into Local 153 of the Office, Professional Employees International Union, whereupon he was “promoted” and promptly fired. He graduated from James Monroe High School in the Bronx and then attended Brooklyn College and the City College of New York. His first position in the labor movement was as an unpaid organizer for Local 155 of the ILGWU. He subsequently went to work for the hatters union (The year was 1953 and hats were still in vogue). His first experience as a $50 per week organizer led to his once again being fired while trying to organize a shop in Hoboken, New Jersey. Moving across the river, he took up new duties for the hatters union in New York City.
He later served in a variety of capacities for the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, including International Representative, Director of Research and Education, Director of Organization; Manager of Local 102, Novelty Hat Workers Union; Administrator of the Local 3 Health Benefit Fund; and Trustee of the Local 80 Health Benefit and Retirement Funds. His responsibilities included organizing and servicing new locals in sixteen states and Puerto Rico, negotiation of collective bargaining agreements, and the drafting and implementation of contracts. In 1966 McNamara left union work to begin his second career as a civil servant.
Mayor John Lindsay recruited McNamara to work in his new administration as the Director of Community Relations for Labor and Industry in the Human Resources Department. In March 1968 McNamara took up new duties as Special Assistant to the Commissioner of Model Cities in the Human Resources Department (MCDA/HRA). In this capacity, he represented the Mayor’s office in negotiations with the building trades (unions and employers associations), community groups and city agencies in launching pilot projects in Model Cities areas. In July 1970, McNamara took on the position of Director of the Building Trades Training Department in New York City’s Manpower and Career Development Agency, part of the Human Resources Administration (HRA, now the Department of Employment). He conceived and implemented Mayor’s Executive Order #20, which required on-the-job training of minority workers in all city-assisted construction.
In October 1973 McNamara took up the position of Director of the Office of Contract Compliance, and Deputy Director of the Bureau of Labor Services, Office of the Mayor, New York City. Here he was instrumental in creating and expanding the new office of C.C./Construction, and in developing rules, regulations, and contract language for New York City’s affirmative action programs. In March 1977 he became the Assistant Commissioner of the New York State Division of Human Rights. Here he supervised the implementation of the Governor’s Executive Orders on Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action, as well as serving as the Director of the Office of State Contract Compliance Programs (E.O.45) and Affirmative Action in State Agencies (E.O. 40). He supervised the administration of state contracts with the Recruitment and Training Program, Inc., for minority recruitment in the building trades.
From September 1981 to January 1983, McNamara served as the Director of the Mayor’s Office of Construction Industry Relations. Reporting directly to the Mayor, he coordinated the City’s activities in combating employment discrimination and extortion in the construction industry. In February 1983, he became a consultant to the New York State Commission of Investigation in connection with a study of the building trades and construction industry practices. He served as an expert witness in public hearings which were conducted as part of the investigation.
In October 1985 he was assigned to the New York State Organized Crime Task Force by the Mayor’s Office and the Commissioner of Investigation to assist in an investigation of the New York building trades and construction industry. In April of 1990 he was assigned to the construction industry project of the New York City Commission of Human Rights and the New York City Office of Labor Services. The investigation focused on race and gender discrimination, and McNamara carried out research in preparation for the public hearings.
In March 1993 McNamara became a consultant to the District Attorney’s Office, County of New York, in the Labor Racketeering Unit. Again, he performed research for investigations of labor racketeering in the construction industry. In 1992 James McNamara retired after a twenty-five year career. In addition to his official duties, McNamara has been active in numerous organizations. He serves on the boards of the Workers Defense League and the Association for Union Democracy. He also serves as the Research Director for the AUD. He is the Secretary and Member of the Board of Directors of the Sixth Avenue Credit Union, Past President of the Gouverneur Gardens Housing Cooperative, a former member and Treasurer of the Board of Directors, Lower Eastside Neighborhood Association, the former Vice Chairman of Local School Board #3 and the Chairman of the Site Selection and Construction Committee.
He has served as an expert witness in numerous cases involving discrimination and corruption in the building trades and construction industry. He has been at the center of the major struggles for the last quarter century in New York City involving the effort to open up the building trades unions to minority workers and to women, along with the repeated efforts of government agencies to clean up corruption in the industry. His wife, Ann Cadmus McNamara, an attorney, was General Counsel, New York City Department of Employment.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1970-1999, includes materials from investigations into corruption in New York City’s District Council of Carpenters dating back to DC President Ted Maritas. This includes the indictment and related cases. Maritas disappeared and his body was never found. However, his wallet and car were found alongside the East River. The trail of corruption and records of litigation continue through the successive government cases against DC President Paschal McGuinness, who resigned from his office and was barred from seeking union office in NYC (He currently holds an executive position within the International Brotherhood of Carpenters); and Fred Devine (found guilty on racketeering charges; case on appeal). Materials include indictments, memoranda; correspondence; transcripts of hearings, and reports of the Independent Review Officer (I.R.O.) charged with oversight in the District Council. Other noteworthy documents in the series include the transcripts of the hearings on corruption at the Jacob Javits Center (Fiorino); the indictment and related records related to the shooting of Carpenters’ official John O’Connor; and the repeated efforts of outspoken members to secure their rights within the union (Macaluso; Clarke; Local 608 hiring hall case). Additional examples of graft and corruption can be found in the records of (former) Bronx Local 17 (Shepis; Moscatiello).
Series II: Mason Tenders Local of the Laborers International Union of North America (LIUNA), 1985-1996, is comprised of records pertaining to racketeering in the Mason Tenders Local of the Laborers International Union of North America (LIUNA), New York City. They document legal actions connected to the Consent Decree entered into by the union in 1994. The outstanding example of testimony related to the case is that of Sammy “the Bull” Gravano, the most famous (and most productive) mobster to testify for the government. Records related to Lou Moscatiello and the declaration of Attorney Roger Levin provide examples of the systemic nature of corruption in the industry.
Series III: International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9, 1967-1995, contains records relating to the long history of corruption and mob control of the International Brotherhood of Painters, District Council 9 in New York City. Repeated efforts to clean up the union have met with failure. The records include correspondence, transcripts of wire taps; indictments; briefs and trial transcripts, along with additional material from active union members related to the internal life of the union (elections; opposition newspapers, flyers, etc.). Press clippings detail the history of mob control and racketeering. Records related to Lou Moscatiello, Bronx mobster, are also included in this series.
Series IV: United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipefitting Industry, Plumbers Local #2 (Manhattan), 1964-1997, contains records related to the government investigation and trial against the officials of Plumbers union, Local #2, Manhattan. After an early morning raid on the offices and homes of top officials, most were tried, convicted and went to jail. The records include press clippings, progress reports, and Department of Labor reports on finances (LM-2s) and the trusteeship (LM-15s). The legal records and briefs document the pattern of corruption in the industry, as does the report “Enforcement Down the Drain.” An important chapter of internal union activity is found in the materials related to the 1996 election in Local 2. The unusually high degree of membership participation and the government efforts to clean up the local were undone when the International merged the local out of existence; members of Local #2 now found themselves in Local #1 (Ozone Park, Queens).
Series V: Service Employees International Union, Local 32 B-J, 1954-1999, includes records that document a rank-and-file campaign within the 32B-J to challenge the corruption of local union officials. The efforts of the reformers led to the ouster of Gus Bevona as president of 32B-J. Bevona had the distinction of being the highest paid union leader in the country (see LM-2s). He was removed by his international president, Andrew Stern, after the reformers succeeded in raising repeated challenges through a variety of campaigns centered on by-law reforms. The corruption within officialdom was given additional exposure with the conviction of business agent McGorman for selling jobs to members. The reformers’ campaign to provide background information to the sentencing judge is documented in the collection.
Series VI: International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1968-1998, consists of records documenting various phases of corruption as well as rank-and-file opposition activity in New York area Teamsters locals. Included are files on Local 807 (the Javits Center local), Tony Salerno and Local 272 (the parking garage local), the government’s case against Barry Feinstein of Local 237, the report issued by the Independent Review Officer on Teamster leader Ron Carey, and Susan Jennik’s brief for the Association for Union Democracy (submitted in relation to U.S. v. IBT, the so-called “Cosa Nostra” case).
Series VII: Building Trades Employers’ Association, 1945-1997, includes materials related to the Association concerning jurisdictional disputes between the building trades.
Series VIII: Unprocessed Material, 1990s-2000s, consists of four boxes of recently donated material, including files on the investigation of Brian McLaughlin as president of the New York City Central Labor Council.
AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council. Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee.; Building Trades Employers' Association.; Carey, Ronald.; Devine, Frederick W.; Fiorino, Anthony D.; Forde, Martin.; Gravano, Salvatore; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City.; Mason Tenders District Council of Greater New York.; McCarron, Douglas J.; McGuinness, Paschal.; McLaughlin, Brian M.; Mosciatello, Louis.; New York (N.Y.). City Commission on Human Rights.; Service Employees International Union. Local 32-B (New York, N.Y.).; Taffet, Allan J.; United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America.; Building trades |x Employees |z New York (State) |z New York.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Construction industry |z New York (State) |z New York.; Construction workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Correspondence.; Discrimination in employment |z New York (State) |z New York.; Fliers (printed matter); Legal files.; New York (N.Y.); Organized crime |z New York (State) |z New York.; Reports.
- Series I: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1970-1999.
  - Affirmative Action: Apprentice and Journeyman Training, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Association for Union Democracy, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benefit Funds, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and Press, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and Press, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings and Press, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings and Press, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cohen, Bernard: Indictment, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: District Council and International, undated, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Corruption and Racketeering: Resource Materials, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Devine, Frederick, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Elections: Campaign Materials, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Elections: Procedures and Rules, 1987, 1995, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Forde, Martin: Indictment, Decision, Memorandum of Sentencing, undated; 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hannah, Thomas J. and Eugene Shoehigh v. Sigurd Lucassen, et al., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Heaney, Robert v. Dockbuilders, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Holden, John et al. v. Local 608, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Investigations and Review Officer (IRO): 1st Interim Report (Javits Center), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - IRO: 1st Interim Report (Javits Center): Exhibits, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - IRO: 2nd Interim Report and Exhibits 1-10, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - IRO: 2nd Interim Report: Exhibits 11-25, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - IRO: 2nd Interim Report: Exhibits 26-36, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - IRO: 3rd Interim Report, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - IRO: 9th Interim Report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - IRO: 10th Interim Report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - IRO: 10th Interim Report: Exhibits, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - IRO v. Anthony D. Fiorino: Exhibits 1-10, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - IRO v. Anthony D. Fiorino: Exhibits 11-32, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - IRO v. Anthony D. Fiorino: Exhibits 33-53, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Javits Center: Agreement, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Javits Center: Hearings, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Job Referral Rules, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Local 17 (Bronx), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Local 46 (Northern California): Linda Eldredge et al. v., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Local 135: Correspondence, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Local 257, 1985, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Local 608: Blackballing, By-Laws, 1990, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Local 608: Hiring Hall, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Local 608: Macaluso, Gaetano: Complaint and Trials, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Local 902, undated, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Local 964: Sopko Indictment, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Local 1456: Complaint, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Local 1456: Frank V. Melia, Charges against, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Local 2287: History of Racketeering, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - McCarron, Douglas J.: Committee for Hearing on Affairs of New York City Vicinity and District Council, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - McCarron, Douglas J.: Testimony to Congressional Subcommittee on Employee-Employer Relations, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - McGuinness, Paschal, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - McNamara, James: Correspondence and Notes, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - New York State v. Attilio Bitondo and Gene Hanley, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - New York State v. Irving Zeidman, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - O’Connor, John: Indictment, Statement, Plea, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Organized Crime Task Force, 1987, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Organizing, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Rank and File Activity, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rank and File Correspondence, 1991-1997 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rank and File Publications, 1983-1997 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Re-Structuring Plan, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Schepis, Benedetto: Charges and Indictment, 1995, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Stirling Homex Corp.: Injunctive Action Against, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Testimonial Dinner: Program, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - United Brotherhood of Carpenters (UBC) v. Adler, Burns, and Empire Contract Consulting Inc., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - United States v. Crea, Steven et al., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - United States v. District Council of New York, UBC (US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722), 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Complaint, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Consent Decrees, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Depositions, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Deposition of Gaetano Macaluso (I), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Deposition of Gaetano Macaluso (II), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Deposition of Marcello Svedese, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Memo of Plaintiff in Opposition to Dismissal, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Memo in Support of Motion for Preliminary Relief, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - US v. DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Stipulation and Order, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - US v DC, 90 Civ. 5722: Testimony of Kenneth McCabe (Investigator), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - United States v. Theodore Maritas et al., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - United States v. Standard Drywall et al., 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - United States v. Waller, Robert (Local 531) and Aninno, Edward (Local 282, IBT), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - United States Department of Labor v. Frederick Devine et al., 1996 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - United States Department of Labor v. United Brotherhood of Carpenters, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Series II: Mason Tenders Local of the Laborers International Union of North America (LIUNA), 1985-1996.
  - Clippings, 1985, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Complaint (Mason Tenders funds v. Messera et al.) I, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Complaint (Mason Tenders funds v. Messera et al.) II, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Contracts, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Indictments, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Levin, Roger, 1990, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Moscatiello, Lou, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Soussi, Albert, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Trust Funds: Statement of Frank Lupo, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - United States of America v. Cervone, Joseph et al., undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - United States of America v. Mason Tenders District Council of Greater New York et al. (USA v. Mason Tenders): 2nd Report of Monitor to the Court, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: 3rd Report of Monitor to the Court, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Complaint, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Consent Decree, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Gravano, Salvatore, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Levin, Roger M., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 1, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 2-6, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 7-30, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 31-40, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 43-48, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 49-59, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 61-80, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 81-93, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 94-105, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 106-111, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 112-116, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 117-120, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - USA v. Mason Tenders: Declaration: Taffet, Allan N., Exhibit 121-130, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 29)